Guide to the Hazelwitch Productions Inc. Records
University of Houston Libraries
Hazelwitch Productions Inc. Records
1981-1998
1997-004
Hazelwitch Productions
1.75 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The collection contains financial, promotional, and managerial records of Hazelwitch Productions from the date of its receipt of Certificate of Operation in July 1981 to its final production in 1996.
Historical Note:
Hazelwitch Productions was established in 1981 by a group of women dedicated to bringing lesbian and feminist performers to the Houston community. The organization was incorporated in April 1983 and, over a fifteen year period, produced around forty events featuring musicians, comedians, and performance artists. In addition to performances, Hazelwitch presented films, workshops, and counseling sessions.
At any one time there were between three and five active members in the corporation, supported by a network of secondary members and volunteers. Key members were Cheryl Wolfarth (the organization's founder), Tori Williams, Pokey Anderson, Cindy Edwards, Katherine Hubbard, Kathy Wilcox, and Gail Eldridge. Remembering Hazelwitch, Kathy Wilcox stressed the cooperative nature of the corporation's management and pointed out that officers were chosen for legal reasons only; decisions were made by consensus in an atmosphere of mutual support and with a strong commitment to feminist ideals.
Although Hazelwitch did not publish a newsletter, events were promoted through the local gay/lesbian press. One notable publicity outlet was "The Wand," the newsletter of the lesbian collective "Womynspace" which had been active since the mid 1980s and has produced the group "Lesbians Over the Age of Fifty," or "L.O.A.F." Pokey Anderson and Cheryl Wolfarth also publicized Hazelwitch on a KPFT radio show which aired until 1994.
Typical venues for productions were churches, restaurants, university auditoriums, and theaters, and Hazelwitch engaged the Houston Area Women's Center and local area bookstores, among others, as outlets for ticket sales. The corporation also enjoyed the sponsorship of organizations such as the University of Houston chapter of N.O.W. and the Montrose Counseling Center. In turn they donated proceedings to groups such as the Aids Foundation of Houston and KPFT Radio.
Despite frugal financial management the 1990s brought difficulties for the corporation due to a decline in ticket sales to Hazelwitch events. Patty Larkin's appearance at the Heinen Theatre in March 1996 was the corporation's last major production, and the process of dissolution was initiated that same year. As lesbian performers have begun to enjoy more mainstream success, their need for the kind of close-knit community support, which Hazelwitch provided, has apparently waned. Nevertheless, it is largely due to the groundbreaking efforts of organizations such as Hazelwitch that this on-going transition to the mainstream is possible.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Hazelwitch Productions
Genre/Form of Material:
Administrative records; Financial records; Fliers (printed matter)
Topical Term:
Entertainers -- Texas -- Houston; Lesbians -- Texas -- Houston
Acquisition Information:
Donation, 1997. Additional materials acquired summer 1998.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains financial, promotional, and managerial records of Hazelwitch Productions from the date of its receipt of Certificate of Operation in July 1981 to its final production in 1996. With the exception of some of the financial records, there was no consistent scheme of organization in the collection. Material is arranged in five series: Financial Records, Production Management, Promotional Material, Dissolution Materials, and Miscellaneous. Financial records constitute two-thirds of the collection. Although there is no documentation of finances before the organization's incorporation in 1983, evidence of detailed accounting, and tax records from 1984-1996 provide insight into the day-to-day running of the corporation during these years.
There is very little correspondence in the collection, but dated notes and performance agreements document management of the corporation's productions from 1989-1996. The collection provides very little coverage of performances before 1989, beyond an inclusive collection of promotional material from 1982-1996.
The last two series in the collection, Miscellaneous and Dissolution Materials, were added to the collection separately during the summer of 1998, and were therefore processed separately. They contain financial materials and material pertaining to productions. The collection also contains two placards; both have been placed in the Miscellaneous sub-series. The larger placard has been stored separately from the Hazelwitch collection; it is stored with oversize materials from other collections.
Detailed List of Contents
- Financial Records
  Scope and Contents
  There are forty-six folders in this series dating from 1984-1996. Initially, all receipts of purchases, telephone bills, postal service invoices, and receipts of deposits made, were kept with duplicates of checks written from the Hazelwitch account. These records have been maintained in this order in folders 12-21. After 1987 check duplicates were filed separately and were apparently not retained after 1990. Folder 22 contains a package of records, which had been collected separately, possibly for the purpose of preparing tax returns. In general no consistent filing scheme was used for receipts and bills after 1989 and receipts have been organized in chronological order by date of purchase. Of particular note from this period are the financial statements prepared by Katherine Hubbard from 1992-1995, which reveal the financial status of Hazelwitch Productions, Inc. during its final years of operation. Tax records in the series include franchise tax reports, corporation income tax returns and all supporting documentation. These were filed by year and have been retained in their original order.
  - Bank Account Agreements, 1986-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bank Statements, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bank Statements, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bank Statements, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bank Statements, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bank Statements, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bank Statements, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bank Statements, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bank Statements, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bank Statements, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bank Statement, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bills, Checks, Deposits, and Receipts (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
  - Bills, Checks, Deposits, and Receipts, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bills, Checks, Deposits, and Receipts, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 16-21)
  - Bills, Deposits, and Receipts, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Check Duplicates, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Check Register Book, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Checks Returned, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Deposits, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Financial Statements, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Financial Statements, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Notes and Worksheets, 1990-1996 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Receipts, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Receipts, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Receipts, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Receipts, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Receipts, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Receipts, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Receipts - Telephone Bills, 1990-1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Tax Records, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Tax Records, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Tax Records, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Tax Records, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Tax Records, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Tax Records, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Tax Records - Amended Returns for 1988 and 1989, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Tax Records, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Tax Records, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Tax Records, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Production Management
  The eighteen folders in this series contain material from 1981-1996. The notes in folders 20-24 document meetings of Hazelwitch members and plans for productions. Folders 25-31 contain papers that cover all aspects of performance agreements with artists: technical, personal and housing riders, exhibit agreements, contract/budget settlement riders, and public appearance agreements. They also contain worksheets drawn up by Hazelwitch staff in preparation for shows. Papers are grouped by performer to reflect their original order. Documents pertaining to the legal status of the corporation are also included in this series.
  - Articles of Incorporation and Statutory Filings, 1981-1994 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Blank Forms and Stationery, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Contracts and Policy Statements, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1993-1996 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Mailbox Service Agreements, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Notes, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Notes, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Notes, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Notes, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Notes, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Performance Agreements - Adam, Margie, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Performance Agreements - Clinton, Kate, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Performance Agreements - Larkin, Patty, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Performance Agreements - Reed, Ann, 1991-1995 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Performance Agreements - Roderick, Libby, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Performance Agreements - Therapy Sisters, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Performance Agreements - Westenhoefer, Susan, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Promotional Material
  There are sixteen folders in this series containing flyers of productions, completed mailing list request forms, and publicity material which dates from 1982-1986. Four sets of returned invitations mailed during 1995 and 1996 constitute the bulk of the series. Notable in the series is the commemorative packet "A Trip Down Memory Lane With Hazelwitch Productions," a collection of flyers advertising the corporation's productions and events from 1982-1996. These were removed from their original file for the purpose of preservation. This series also contains an oversized promotional display board celebrating fifteen years of Hazelwitch productions.
  - A Trip Down Memory Lane With Hazelwitch Productions, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - A Trip Down Memory Lane With Hazelwitch Productions, 1987-1996 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Mailing List Additions A-I, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Mailing List Additions J-Z, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Production Lists, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Publicity Material, 1990-1993 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Publicity Material, 1993-1996 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Returned Invitations A-F, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Returned Invitations G-O, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Returned Invitations P-Z, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Returned Invitations A-I, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Returned Invitations J-Z, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Returned Invitations A-Z, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Returned Invitations A-M, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Returned Invitations N-Z, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Dissolution Materials
  This series contains fifteen folders, dating from 1990-1998. This series arrived at a later date than the bulk of the collection and was therefore processed separately. The bulk of the series, however, dates from 1996-1998, and holds financial records and correspondence relating to the dissolution of Hazelwitch. The series contains information regarding the disposition of the final funds of the organization, which may be of interest to the researcher.
  - Bank Statements, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bank Statements, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bank Statements, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Bank Statements, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Bank Statements, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Check Register Book, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Check Register Book, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Check Register Book, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Check Register Book, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Financial Statements, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Franchise Tax and Annual Public Information Report, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Budget, March 3, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Final Disbursement Information, 1996-1998 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Records, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Mailing List, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Miscellaneous
  This series contains six folders, dating from 1994-1996. This series arrived at a later date than the bulk of the collection and was therefore processed separately. Materials include Patty Larkin Performance, Venue Information, Calendar and Miscellaneous Entertainment. This series includes two placards. The larger tri-fold one has been placed with oversize materials from other collections.
  - Patty Larkin Performance, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Venue Information, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Calendar, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous Entertainment, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Small Placard (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Large Tri-Fold Placard, undated